A friend of mine recently was diagnosed
with a rare disease and he had some lab
work done and he called me on the phone
and said, "Hey, I know what I have. I
have celiac disease." I said, "What do
you mean?" Well, here's the blood work.
When I looked at the blood work, I'm a
physician, right? I've been trained.
I've seen patients for 10 years. I
looked at I said, "What makes you think
this is showing that you have celiac
disease?" Cuz all the labs were
negative. He said, "Oh, no, no, no. Look
here." I'm like, "No, no, no. You're
misreading it. It doesn't say what you
think it says." Sounds a little snobby
for me as an expert to say you need the
experts, but honest to God, I really do
think you need the experts. And I don't
think that chat GBT or Claude can take
the place of that.
Well, welcome back to the Sigma Room
where we dig into how AI, data, and real
world healthcare actually come together
in practice. Today, I'm excited to be
joined by Dr. Steven Labkoff. He's a
physician executive and an AI platform
leader who spent his career figuring out
how to turn clinical, genomic, and real
world data into tools that actually move
the needle. in drug discovery, clinical
research and patient care. He trained in
internal medicine and cardiology. He
went on to lead informatics and data
platform work at organizations like
Fizer and Astroenica and the multiple
amyoma research foundation where he
served as the chief data officer. And
today he's a busy guy. He's running
Luminant Consulting. He collaborates
with the division of clinical
informatics at Beth Israel Deaconist
Medical Center and he hosts the
Practical AI in Healthcare podcast.
Steve, thanks for being here and it's
really great to have you. Welcome to the
Signal Room.
Hey, my pleasure. Thank you very much
for having me.
Well, I want to just jump in because,
you know, we've had some interesting
conversations and I know that you've got
a lot of things that you're you're
working on. So, I wanted to start with
what's top of mind for you as you're
looking at healthcare and AI right now.
What's really occupying most of your
thinking lately? And, you know, what are
you really paying the closest attention
to? There's just so much to talk about.
I wouldn't even know where to start, but
love to hear from your perspective. So,
you know, right now, it's funny. I was
in a conversation just within the last
hour with somebody and I mentioning he
asked me basically the same question
because I didn't really set out to
become sort of a like a pundit in the
space, but it because of the podcast and
the other work I'm doing and the
publications, people are calling me and
asking me questions like this. So, this
guy asked me, you know, the same
question. What's the most pressing
thing? What's the the latest trends that
you're seeing? And I'm going to talk
more about like the things that are sort
of not the trends as much, but the
things that I'm seeing that I think are
really important things to pay attention
to. And it goes back to some of the work
I did most recently when I was the VP of
analytics at Bristol Myers Squibb. And
what I observed while I was there was
that when they were trying to roll out
AI, one of the things I observed was
that it's such a new technology. And by
the way, it is a technology. People
think that it's not a an information
technology. It really is and it needs to
be thought of in that framework. Vast
majority of leaders in the organization,
both senior leaders and middle managers
and folks at the bottom of the stack,
you know, the secretaries and the
administrative assistants, the amount of
these folks who actually understood what
AI could potentially do was tiny.
Certainly there was a group in the IT
department that was very well-versed in
it and understood things like what's
possible and what you could do but it
was a very very tiny percentage of the
senior leadership and anywhere in the
organ that actually understood it in a
meaningful way which led me in the work
that I was doing that I am doing at the
Beth Israel Deaconist medical center at
the division of clinical formatics into
our last fall conference that we ran and
that was called signal to the noise.
purpose of the conference was to sort of
try to identify the types of AI
solutions in healthcare that are making
a difference kind of like what you
described in the opening and one of the
things we kind of trip tripped into was
this concept of AI literacy and it's one
of the least talked about AI issues that
are out there I mean other things people
are talking about are governance and
safety and and those are all important
but the one that's not getting a lot of
airplay is this issue of of of literacy
and it's one of I think if it's not the
most important thing that's out there.
It's it's up there in the top three
because we're seeing hype and trends and
and everything and things are moving at
lightning speed, but most of the world
doesn't quite understand yet what's
possible and what it could do for you.
And that's kind of where lit the whole
literacy conversation begins.
Yeah, it's such an important point. the
crazy pace that things have happened now
with the emergence of open AI and uh the
anthropic kind of jumping way out ahead
and getting going direct to the p to the
public and you know potentially
impacting how patients are thinking
about their care inside of health
systems. We really have to get our
ourselves organized quickly and start to
help people understand this stuff.
Brilliant point to to bring that up.
There's so many different kinds of AI,
but not all of it's not all of it's how
people are thinking about it and and I
think that's where it gets a little
little sideways because you mentioned
it's it really is technology. We've been
technology first for a long time, but
we've done not so well when it comes to
helping people understand what the
intended uses are, what it's good for,
what it's not, and even worse, we've not
really gotten to the people who were
impacted by the workflow before we
actually designed something.
That's exactly right. Yeah.
That how has that been in your
experience? Have you seen a lot more of
that that kind of technology first
approach or or
No. Well, no. people could people seem
to be at the moment from what what I'm
what I'm observing is they they are
treating this as something super novel
super new and they're not using the same
type of critical thinking that has
typically accompanied every other type
of new technological innovation that's
happened over the last call it 30 years.
So you and I are in the same age group.
We both cut our teeth in the late 90s or
maybe the mid 90s as we got into this
space. And you'll remember, you know,
when the internet started, the internet
was another exactly the same kind of of
of a hype cycle. Same kind of like you
can do everything. It's going to change
the way we're doing the entire world.
But it wasn't until the mid 2000s, maybe
very very Yeah. like 2004, fiveish, when
Amazon, eBay, and all these other big
companies really found their footing.
And we figured out that in 1993 or '94,
'95 when it was, you know, Netscape and
it was just so cool, nobody knew exactly
what to do until they realized, oh, we
can sell things on the internet. We can
search for things on the internet. we
can get data from the and I think we're
in the same kind of a we're only three
years into this whole journey with AI
and I think we still don't yet know
where things are going to settle. I mean
people have been talking about AI in you
know in how to practice medicine and
clinical decision support and how to
ensure that patient you know we're going
to change medicine well yeah we are
going to change medicine but it's going
to change probably not at the pace that
people are hyping it about and that was
what one of the things that came out of
our work at the at the Beth Israel is
that there are some really interesting
things happening like we've had people
talk about everything from diabetic
retinopathy screening and and pathology
and things like that. And yeah, AI can
do in some cases a better job than
humans in diagnosing these things and
helping doctors think better, but I'm
not clear if that's where the real wins
are going to settle out. One of the
things we've seen also is that the
mundane use cases, use cases for things
that are really like really hanging up
humans, pushing paper for example.
Yeah,
I was just chiding with a friend of
mine. I run my consultancy and I don't
do my own billing. So, my clients love
that because I don't bill them and then
and then, you know, I have to sit down
and spend an hour or two doing my
billing and I it's a task that I just
loathe doing. It's just a painful thing
even though I need it to get paid. But,
if I could figure out an AI agent that
will help me with something as mundane
as getting my bills out the door on time
at the beginning of the month, that
would be a win, right? And it it'd be a
great win, like if it helps diagnose
rare disease or if it helps us generate
new drugs. All these things are really
really cool use cases, but they're not I
think they're those use cases are going
to be they're not going to be the ones
that are going to really win the day, so
to speak. It's not the ones are going to
win the hearts and minds of the of the
masses because the masses don't know
anything about AlphaFold. They don't
know anything about how to design a
drug. They know that the only thing in
their checkbook is a painful thing to do
every month. And what do we do?
Yes. Yeah. I I think the the interesting
opportunities for me and you know I'm
sure you have some some thoughts around
this and probably you're involved in
some things in this space too but the
potential research is the part that I
get excited about if nothing more than
the fact that having capability to
process information uh at a scale that
we've never been able to at a time frame
in a pace that we've never been able to
that really kind of excites me but the
data hygiene and data quality stuff
we've got to get on that stuff and we've
been how long we've been talking about
interoperability and we've really not
achieved any level of it. That really
moves the needle and relieves a lot of
the burden for clinicians that has been
routinely had things added to their
their list of data points they've got to
capture conversations you have to have
about certain things so it's documented
can be built. I mean all that stuff we
just kind of went in the wrong direction
but we've got we got to get serious. We
don't have a lot of time. I don't think
I I you know, I don't know about how
much time we have, but I do think that
you're not wrong in that we need to have
be thinking about this a little
differently than we may have thought of
in the past. We need to be or maybe
stated it slightly differently. We need
to think about it with the same
framework as things that we've done in
the past because at the end of the day,
if you think about it like a standard
information technology play or or
challenge, you have there there are
rules and and ways of working that have
been tried and true for 40 years about
how to bring a new technology to bear.
And I think right now most of the world
is kind of ignoring that because they're
so enamored with all the really cool
things, all the new video clips that can
be made, all the artificial photographs
that can be done. And all those things
are really cool and really interesting
and, you know, to some degree a little
concerning when you have, you know,
artificial people talking and they look
like President Trump or President Obama.
Those things are highly concerning. But
if we take a step back and look at it
with the same lens that we use for
looking at any new physical technology
that we bring into our lives, it's going
to look a lot different. So initially
people are going to start using it for
the things that they know how to do and
we'll take over for the for those
things. But that's not going to be the
real win. The real win is going to be
when you're thinking completely out of
the box and you come up with new use
cases that is very specifically
earmarked for what AI can literally do
differently than other than like do your
checkbook differently or the same as you
do it now. you need to come and and I
think that's where time will settle out
and these use cases are going to you
know start to bubbling to the surface
and we're seeing that and the podcast
you mentioned I did this podcast so
Practical AI in Healthcare is all about
looking for exactly that what are the
what are the bright spots in the
healthcare ecosystem whether it's in
patient care or nursing or engaged
patients or life sciences where are the
bright spots where these things are
being found and what are those bright
spots and that's one of the core
missions of why we do that podcast.
I would love to like just rewind just a
little and just kind of talk a little
bit about what inspired you and kind of
led you into this because you mentioned
earlier, you know, you didn't set out to
be dealing with data and AI at the and
that's, you know, as a clinician. It's
not like you didn't have a lot of other
things you could do.
So, if you rewind my career, I started
as a as a an internal medicine doctor. I
trained at University of Pittsburgh,
which was an amazing place to get
trained. It was kind of the best of both
worlds. It had both inner city
components and a lot of suburban
components. So, you'd see some of the
really nasty things that you need to see
when you're in training because of the
downtown kind of parts of it. And then
you'd see a lot of uh high-end like we
had chics coming into Pittsburgh from
the Middle East who needed liver
transplants and and their children and
their and we would see these high-end
patients and the very low-end pat. So, I
got my training in that environment
which was amazing place to train. But
while I was there, I got hooked up with
um the division of informatics that was
run by a guy named Randy Miller at the
time. And I got hooked into doing some
work and it was I'm going to call it
peeon work because they were working on
an artificial intelligence system called
the quick medical reference or QMR. And
I was one of these residents that got
hired to do a lot of research to create
these medic these um they call them
disease profiles. And they was looking
for the weights. How do you come up with
a profile that was using a deterministic
model to determine whether or not the
patient had this given disease? And I
got to meet the department and I got to
meet all these people in the in the
field. And eventually after I did my
cardiology work, I decided to go do a
fellowship in informat left cardiology
and went to Harvard and MIT to do a
clinical informatics fellowship at Beth
at Brigham Women's Hospital at MIT. It
was a combined fellowship between the
two programs. spent some time up in
Boston uh and then left Boston after the
fellowship and faculty was done and went
to life sciences. I got hired by Fizer
and for 13 amazing years I got to do
things that were not what a typical
doctor in pharmaceuticals gets to do.
Like I was not it's called an a medical
science liaison or an MSL. I wasn't
working on the clinical trial space. I
was working on the cutting edge of
healthcare technology and how it was
affecting the life sciences industry.
And that was an amazing thing to do. I
mean it led me into programs and things
that were that I haven't been able to
rival since. Like I got to build a
hospital in Africa in Kapala Uganda. So
for four years I was going back and
forth to Kala and orchestrating all the
healthcare IT infrastructure for this
hospital. And by the way, if you ask me
what I knew about building hospitals
when I started, I didn't have the
slightest clue and let alone doing it in
subsaharan Africa. But over the course
of the time I was there, we built out
the infrastructure. We treated it like
another technology program with
different constraints. I raised almost
$2 and a half million dollars in funding
and and donations and kind from places
like Compact Computer and Gillet Packard
and IBM and and SAS the statistics
company and we got licenses and we got
hardware. We implemented all this stuff.
The the organization is called the
infectious disease institute and
recently interviewed somebody for the
podcast who's working there. It's still
there. It's still up and running 20
years later after I was done with Fizer
and all these interesting things. Well,
actually just before I left, I started a
department there called Healthcare
Informatics, which was looking at the
policy implications of what uh
healthcare informatics was doing to the
industry. And I actually was almost like
a lobbyist. I was in Washington twice a
week briefing senates and health
staffers on on on e-rescribing and and
standards and other things and started
that group up back in those days. Fast
forward, I ended up doing another stint
at Astroenica on real world evidence. I
started three departments there in real
world evidence and biomarkers and
clinical trial design. A few years
later, uh, ended up as the chief data
officer at the multiple myyoma research
foundation, building out one of the
biggest medical registries ever stood
up, uh, to study myyoma, the the can the
blood cancer, the bone cancer. And then
most recently, as I said earlier, I was
the VP of analytics for clinical
operations and medical affairs at
Bristol Myers Squibb until uh they went
through a major downsizing, 10% cuts.
They missed a bunch of trials and I
struck out and started doing my uh my
consulting through Luminant Consulting,
which is my current firm.
That that is amazing. I I I don't think
I've ever heard anybody rattle off all
the anywhere near the number of things
that you did that just not typical for a
physician to be doing extraordinary. I I
it's nuts.
I hear the passion that that you have.
There's no mistaking that. But I I want
to kind of get into what you're doing
now, but maybe talk a little bit about
what is it now that's driving you and
keeping you so engaged. I mean, it's
it's got to be really demanding. And by
the way, I mean I I happened to know
from having our previous conversation
that you also raised a family during all
this activity that you were doing.
Amazing. Amazing to me. But please just
just tell me what are some of the things
that really get you excited and are
motivating you and the things that
you're working on now and maybe start to
talk a little bit about what some of
those things are. Well, every time
there's been an interesting new novel
thing in healthcare, I I've kind of
gotten involved at the beginning of it.
And when I started my fellowship at
Harvard, it was handheld computers. And
I did one I did the very first major
study of how they use handheld computers
in clinical care back in 1993,9495.
And that got published. It was I did it
in concert with Apple. It was using
Apple Newton's. Uh we spun out a small
business called Skyscape Computing.
Anyway, fast forward like what's getting
me up to date now is like again we're
another inflection point with some
really interesting innovations to
medicine. And when I saw, you know, I
knew about Chachi in the fall of 22, but
when I went to him in in the spring of
like March of 23 and I saw like how
crazed the world got in such a short
period of time, I was like, "Wow, this
is a game changer. I got to get myself
involved in this. I want to be an expert
in this. I want to get I want to just
get become completely in the weeds with
all this stuff. And I did and I and I
had actually already had my appointment
at the Beth Israel. I convinced them
that this was the most important new
topic in healthcare informatics that has
happened in 25 years. I I convinced them
to run these conferences. We've
published one, two, almost six papers
now on the topic. We try to influence
policy at the highest levels through
this. And what gets me excited is like
being here and learning and continuing
to try to have impact and to sort of
help in some ways try to steer the not
the ship so much but at least you know
call out where there's issues that
people aren't paying attention to like
the healthcare literacy. The other thing
we called out was, you know, this other
issue of we we published four papers out
of our first conference and we looked at
at AI governance in healthcare and we
looked at how it's affecting patients
and how it's affecting real world
evidence and I I was the lead author on
one on clinical decision support. These
are all issues which are they're the
earliest places where people are
planting flags and trying to get some
value out of out of AI. And we want to
make sure I want to make sure that it's
safe for patients that it's providing
credible trustworthy information and
that the world in general is not going
to go down weird rabbit holes on things
because of hallucination, but that we
actually are looking at it with a
critical eye. And I'm actually, you
know, that critical eye piece is quite
important because I'm afraid what we're
going to see is like the dumbing down of
medicine. And I say that with a lot of
concern to be honest. Like you want to
what's my biggest concern? That's one of
the biggest concerns that I have is that
medicine will it's already getting
dumbed down in some respects. And it's
going to get a lot worse because people
are going to become overly dependent and
overrusting of what's they're being
told. And maybe or maybe not without
good reason because you know Claude and
Chacht are just spectacularly good at
what they're doing now. and it's only
been three years. This is that means
it's the worst it's ever going to be in
our lifetime is now. It's only going to
get better.
Yeah. That's the piece that's, you know,
a little worrisome to me. I mean, I know
you you work with this technology
yourself. So, the people that are not uh
as involved there are using it a whole
lot. They're not seeing some of the the
flaws that that you and I are coming
just running into on a daily basis with
it because it just it drifts the line of
questioning and the prompting that you
do actually affects it. It just
continues to it can spin way out out of
alignment for the things that you're
trying to do with it.
Yeah.
And it's so complimentary. I mean I
think it thinks I'm a really super nice
guy. I'm sure it loves you too.
Oh, I named my chat GPT voice. I call
her Zora in uh in homage to the computer
on Star Trek Discovery. And you know,
it's funny. There's people use these
tools in a lot of different ways. And I
tend to use I don't generally use it
like a search engine. I sometimes I do,
but what I try to do is I I like to see
the world through a systems approach.
And I try to help get it to help me
connect the dots to try to see the
things I'm not seeing in terms of let's
say three or four big things that are
happening. concurrently and I try to
figure out how to, you know, do they
connect? If they do connect, what are
those connections? Are those connections
something that could be influenced? Are
they things that we should be concerned
about or should we be double downing,
you know, doubling down on them, you
know, and and I find it to be a really
helpful thought partner, but that also
means that it I don't have to
necessarily trust what it's telling me.
I actually I'm using my own critical
thinking and it's working as a as a
helper with that. My concern is that you
ask it things and it gives you
interesting answers that sound really
credible and that you just take it
hookline and sinker and don't don't test
it.
Yeah.
I I can't even tell you how many times I
tried to train it not to do certain
things and the very next thing it does
is exactly what it just agreed it
wouldn't do.
Yeah, of course.
It's like dealing with a child in some
ways.
Well, and by the way, do certain
behaviors when you you can condition
them better than you condition AI. I
think well I was working on a I have a
client that was coming up with a a deck
to to create for them and I've you know
started using Notebook LM to do uh nice
graphics and writing slide decks is a
one of the it's like balancing your
checkbook. It's one thing I really can't
stand in life and notebook does a nice
job. So I was working on it this
morning. I gave it a really good prompt
and and I gave it all the the details I
wanted it to do and it came back and it
was like 95% right and it said okay edit
the slides. And I gave it edits on each
slide. And what did it do? It messed up
slides. There was nothing wrong with
them. So I ended up having to like
download three or four versions of what
I was working on and picking and
choosing the slides that were right to
get the final product. It didn't hone it
to a way to just continually get the one
work product better. It kind of went
down weird rabbit holes and like it
completely took labels off of graphs and
and things like that that made it and
like why why would you do that? It's and
I didn't even give you the instruction
to change it. Like I there was a couple,
you know, garbage text in there and I
said fix the garbage and and it fixed
that but it messed up three other
things. So
it's almost like you're just you were
sitting here with me till the wee hours
of this morning because I was I was
wrestling and fighting
with with collage trying to get
something, you know, straightened out
from a formatting standpoint. I was
having it compared to a brand that was
actually, you know, already structured
in one of my websites. It just decided
that something else was more on brand
and it just manufactured something
completely different.
Yeah. Like
I never proted to do any of that. And
yeah, so if people are afraid it's going
to take their job, just pay attention to
just a little bit and and start learning
how to use it, you'll feel better about
Well, that's like that's and that's the
literacy piece, right? Like if people
understand number one, it's not going to
replace your job. In fact, it's going to
make your job different. You're gonna
have to be using critical thinking with
AI a whole lot more than people were
realizing. It's not going to be the
thing that's g in certain places where
it's doing and people I think confuse AI
with machine learning. So machine
learning techniques that are used in
artificial vision and like radiology and
pathology that's a whole that's a
different beast right and it's been
demonstrated and proven that those
machine learning techniques are good in
fact can be better than humans in terms
of recognizing tumors and recognizing
pathological disease. That's different
than working with a large language
model. And people are just bundling it
all together and assuming it's all one
thing. It's not one thing. It's like,
you know, it's the same with internet
back in the in the 90s and early 2000s.
You know, you've got websites that can
just be brochureware. You've got
websites that can be search engines.
You've got websites that can be
e-commerce things. And each one is
different. Each one has a different
reason for existing. And you need to
look at each one with a different lens
to figure that all out. I mean, I keep
using this lens thing. I you one of the
things you didn't mention about me is
that I'm actually a professional
photographer in the background and uh I
do
you don't have enough to do
well you know when my kids left home and
I used to be their soccer coach and I
would do all those things with them I
needed something to do with a with the
spare time I had from not coaching
little league soccer right so I got into
photography in a big way and uh I've I
compete at the national and
international level and I've won many
awards at those levels and uh my
favorite topic though is is
astrophotography. I like to shoot
pictures of galaxies and nebulas and
comets and things like that.
That's that's fascinating. Well, you're
dealing with uh with clients now. I
mean, obviously there's some some bigger
challenges that you see, but wonder if
there's some some things that you're
kind of excited about because you see
organizations starting to get some
things right and and moving into some
much more meaningful applications on the
So, one of the clients that I'm I
haven't signed yet. I'm not going to say
who they are, but they this is an
organization I I've known for many years
and I look at them as a they're an
academic institution and they are
finally it's finally dawning on them
that they can use AI that their business
is going to rely on AI. So they get
government they're very much government
funded but they realized they can't
continue with that. The last couple
years of the current administration has
seen to it that relying on government
grants is not going to be a long-term
sustainable way of thinking and they see
that and they're trying to bring their
organization around into being a lot
more focused on the data. I I've been a
proponent in in life sciences that life
science companies have for generations
believed that their work product, the
final product that they have is a pill
or injection or some kind of therapy.
And I look at it with a different lens.
I look at it and say, you absolutely
never send the FDA a pill. What do you
send the FDA? You send the FDA a hard
drive full of data. You send them
information about the pill. You send
them information about safety. You send
them information about clinical trial
results and what you send them is data.
So to me treating data as a product like
it's the most logical thing that you can
imagine. So what I've been seeing lately
is that some companies are starting to
understand that in order for them to
survive into the next call it 15 to 20
years if they haven't been using their
data or thinking about their data in
that framework that they are going to be
like the locomotive engine in 1940 that
is precisely what's going to happen.
They will be they will be the the the
metaphorical locomotive when jet engines
have come around and jets are starting
to arrive. They're going to keep doing
their business as if, you know, it's
going to take, you know, 27 hours to go
from New York to Chicago on a on a on
the Zephyr when it takes an hour and a
half to do it on a jet. That entire game
change has hasn't sunk in yet. And those
that are seeing the data is is that jet
engine or at least a jet fuel that
they're the ones if they realize it,
they're the ones who will succeed. There
are companies like there's one out there
called Tempest. Tempest is a biologics
company that was started by a guy names.
And Tempest is a firm that has not just
doubled down but like quadrupled down or
exponentially doubled down on on the
value of data. And in this case it's
genomic data and proteomic data. And
they are one of the leading
organizations out there that that
produces highlevel highquality data in
that domain. And that data is the fuel
that will help us to find the answers to
new diseases, find us new drug targets,
find us new therapies. And it's
companies like them and like Foundation
Medicine and and uh some of the other
bigger bigger firms. But the data is the
product. And largely from my experience,
big pharma has not gotten that yet. big
pharma doesn't they realize that data is
important but they don't treat it with
the same degree of reverence as they do
uh the pill or you know the actual pill
and until they do what's going to happen
is there's going to be upstart companies
that are going to start to pop up and
they will treat the data in the way I'm
describing and those companies are going
to find you know seven to 12x the number
of new targets they're going to find
that they can find patient patients more
easily for their trials. They're going
to find that their inclusion exclusion
criteria are going to be honed better
because when they think about it with an
eye towards the data and getting the
data part of it right, all of a sudden
it changes everything in terms of your
thinking about how do you generate and
go from A to B for the development of of
a new drug or new compound. This is an
interesting space, you know, to me just
because organizations have been for the
longest time very very comfortable to
spend money on technology. Yeah. a
little bit short changing on on the on
data curation and making sure that the
data is in in a usable state and I think
the rapid growth of organizations where
they're onboarding new healthcare
companies whether it's hospitals or
clinics or whatever uh there's
unfortunately not a whole lot of funds
left over to do the the stuff that
people like you and I have to clean up
when it's it's really the data
even the way you just said that people
like you and I have to clean up right
that makes us sound like we're janitors
and at the end of the Hey,
we're not janitors. We are I think of us
like data chemists. We're the ones who
when we we figure out how to purify a a
like when you purify a compound in
chemistry, you're trying to take away
all the impurities. You're trying to get
down to like the crystallin truth of
what the the molecule that you're trying
to synthesize might be. Similarly with
data, you want to use the same approach.
You want to get it down to a crystallin
approach to your data. Make sure it's
clean. It's it's there's nothing that's
missing. Make sure that it is it's
truthful. I mean, there's the the the
Evan V's of of big data, but people use
that as a catch as a catchphrase, but
what they don't do is realize that the
reason that catchphrase exists is
because this is important stuff. And the
data is the jet fuel the for the jet
engine, which is the AI model. And if
you don't have good data, you're going
to get crappy responses out of your
model.
This kind of goes right into I I suspect
that one of the things that really
caused you to come up with a name for
your consulting firm, you know,
ultimately what you're dealing with in
your podcast. There's so much volume of
data that's being generated. It's just,
you know, compounding on a I don't even
know how fast it doubling in size. I
mean, there was a period of time every
24 months all the data in in accumulated
history was doubling. I don't I I have
no idea what that pace is now, but it's
probably exponentially faster than that.
I'd love to hear, you know, really
what's behind the name, you know, Luna
Consulting, then maybe to kind of talk
about, you know, how you're dealing with
all of this volume of data. And I it's
interesting because you use some terms
that in your your uh podcast that that I
I'm partial to. It's really about
signals and noise. We talk about that
side. Still your fun.
Okay. As I mentioned earlier, one of my
hobbies is astrophotography.
astrophotography. It turns out when you
go to try to take a picture of a nebula,
you look up in the night sky. Do you
ever see a nebula? Have you ever seen a
big red blotch in the night sky?
Probably not, right? You never do. But I
promise you, they're there. If you're in
the summertime sky, you can get a
glimmer of it when you see in a very
dark place, you see the Milky Way. But
it turns out the night sky is loaded,
and I mean loaded, with things that you
can see if you know how to look for
them. You have to separate the signal
through the noise. And I've spent the
last seven or eight years methodically
imaging almost every major nebula, every
major galaxy in the northern hemisphere
from Westport, Connecticut, which is
there's an observatory there and I'm a
member there and I get to use their
gear. Luminant comes in because our icon
is that of a star and the star, you
know, I want to be able to see the
stars. I want to be able to see how it
all comes away from the background. And
what we're also doing with Lummit is
we're also forming constellations. So
all the different projects projects we
take on I don't take them on because I
needed I need to take them on. Like I
I'm at a point in my life where I'm
doing this because I really have passion
for it as you probably can tell and I
take it on and I feel like it's a
constellation of different pieces and
you know as you put the stars together
and you can see different patterns that
becomes then your navigation points. It
gives you a way to to navigate through
the pathway of what's out there. So the
that's why the Luminant's icon is that of
a of a blazing star. It's funny. I told
my wife just this morning, I think it's
Beetlejuice is I think because it kind
of looks orange like Beetlejuice.
Beetlejuice is in the upper in the upper
left side of of Orion. It's a very
bright star and it's orange. We'll say
that my logo is Beetlejuice.
I love it. That clearly kind of ties,
you know, I think I've seen this on some
of your profiles too. finding the signal
through the noise and getting getting
the right things like amplifying them. I
think something that was said to me one
time was by a chief data analytics
officer. I think it was it's UPMC I
think it was but she talked about the
number one role in her or was actually a
journalist which I thought was
interesting and she made a really good
point with that and it was not all the
things that you know are going to be
showing up in the Wall Street Journal.
It's the things that are going to inform
decisions that have to be made and
that's h what how CEOs and executives
actually use that kind of data. So it's
there's an art to knowing what's
important and what's not. Love to hear a
little bit how you're how you're
thinking about things with your and how
you're choosing the direction you're
going not only with your you're
consulting for but also in your podcast.
I mean obviously you're you're talking
to some really influential people that
are doing things for wide variety of of
spaces in but all connected to the
things that you're so passionate about.
So you know because I've been in
informatics now for Jesus since 1993
officially but I was kind of doing it in
medical school too. uh I've acquired
quite a rolodex of contacts along the
way and many of these contacts in the
informatics world have filtered
themselves into businesses. Some of them
have filtered themselves into academia,
some of them are in uh PE firms or
venture capital firms. They're all over
the place. And the podcast is sort of
based on trying to understand which of
those souls are doing the most important
work. And we've had to your point, we've
had some very good fortune. We've had
some very high level executives that
actually sought us out. We recently had
a senior executive named Matt Tupo from
Sanopi uh who came and did a two-part
episode with us talking about what
Sanifi is doing with AI. And for those
of you who are interested, this is one
of our best episodes. He was so open and
so informative. It was like I couldn't
believe a pharma company would be that
willing to open the kimono and talk in
detail about what they're doing. and he
was and they did. He did and it's
awesome. But we're also getting other
folks. We're getting medical leaders. We
had Bob Locker who's the chief of
medicine at UCSF. It's a thousand person
internal medicine department, one of the
biggest in the country. He got on our
podcast. We have a member of the of the
federal government will be on in a few
weeks named Jeff Smith who's in the
office of national coordinator and he'll
be talking about US policy around AI and
how it's shaping up in Washington, how
it will affect everybody going forward
and the implications of things that are
happening from the 21st century cure
cures act and things like that. We
choose our guests to try to find those
who have the highest impact, those who
have the best stories to tell and
frankly those who tell good stories.
It's not just enough to have somebody
who's a good has a good thing that
they've done, but they need to be able
to express themselves in a way that is
compelling. We're going to get Zach
Kahani in a few weeks. Uh Zach is the
editor-inchief of New England Journal of
Medicine AI, and he'll be on the
podcast. We're going to record him at
the end of May. And you know, I'm really
fortunate that, you know, because of my
connections over the years that when I
knock on somebody's door, they know me,
they know my reputation, and they're And
it's not just me, by the way. I have a
partner. His name is Lean Rosenblet. And
you know, Leon is like my my right arm
on this project. He's an amazing guy to
help with and I hope that you bring him
on your podcast. He's just a spectacular
partner and uh and a good friend. But
between the two of us, we've been
seeking out sort of the cream and sort
of we want to get that signal from the
podcast out and make sure that we're
getting the best of the best on on our
discussions.
No, I love that. And you know, you know
this, but I mean that was one of the the
reasons I wanted to have you on my
shows. You're a voice that needs to be
heard. And it's really important that
people are are hearing from experts that
are not hobbyists that really they're
doing the doing the research. They're
doing the work to make sure that we're
we're taking things the right direction.
I'm curious all the different
conversations you've been having with
with your guests and your own
observations. Are there patterns or
warning signs that you wish people would
look at and pay attention to that maybe
they're not? I I think one of the
warning signs that I'm seeing or I'm
concerned about is number one, we
mentioned it, the lack of AI literacy
where people are not understanding how
to use these tools in a in a way that is
intelligent. Uh it's not it's not a new
interface for Google. It's not a it's
not a new w version of Wikipedia that
just has the conversation of all all
known information in one place. These
are tools that can connect dots in ways
that people just simply don't get just
yet. I know I have friends, very close
friends who, you know, are trying to use
it to help them diagnose some diseases
that they're they're dealing with. And
the problem I have with that is that it
can do that. But this here's one of my
biggest really biggest concerns of all
actually is that there's been a trend in
the last call it 10 years to quote
unquote democratize data, democratize
information systems. and what that
means. And it I had a very hard time
understanding it when I first heard the
term what it meant to democratize data.
And finally, I I understand it now. And
what it what I believe it means is that
you give lay people access to
information so they can do their own
thinking. They can do their own work and
they can draw their own conclusion. They
so they're not dependent on experts.
They can do it themselves. And therein
lies one of my biggest biggest biggest
concerns. While I know there are people
out there who are citizen scientists, I
know there are people out there who have
trained in other domains and can do this
well, what I'm really afraid of is that
people who don't have that training or
don't have the context work with it and
draw different conclusions from it that
that might even be completely 180
degrees wrong. So, I'll give you an
example and I don't a friend of mine
recently was diagnosed with a rare
disease and he had some lab work done
and he called me on the phone and said,
"Hey, I know what I have. I have celiac
disease." I said, "What do you mean?"
Well, here's the blood work. And I like,
"Oh." When I looked at the blood work
with him, and I'm a physician, right?
I've been trained. I've seen patients
for 10 years. I looked at I said, "What
makes you think this is showing that you
have celiac disease?" Because all the
labs were negative. He's, "Oh, no, no,
no. Look here." I'm like, "No, no, no.
You're misreading it. It doesn't say
what you think it says." And it actually
it did support something that they had
something else that they had, but all
that was was confirmatory that they had
the other problem. So my point here is
that if they look at data without that
critical context, whether it's data that
they get from labcore when they get
their or they look at their medical
records, if they don't have this
clinical context, they have the risk of
making really really bad life decisions.
And I realize it sounds a little snobby
for me as a as an expert to say you need
the experts, but honest to God, I really
do think you need the experts. And I
don't think that the general lay public
has the training or understanding. And I
don't know that chat GBPT or Claude can
take the place of that. Maybe it can,
maybe it will. I don't know that it can
today, but even experts who use these
tool who use these tools today find
there's flaws in there and they're so
convincing that they're correct. These
tools come at you and they they stroke
your ego. They tell you, "Oh, that's a
great idea. Oh, you're thinking about
this in exactly the right way." And
unless you think about it and use these
tools with a very critical eye, you can
be led down a garden path and find
yourself in a in a world of hurt. And
that's my big one of my biggest concerns
here.
I I can tell you from my own experiences
that it's been very very difficult to
push back the whole concept of
democratizing the data particularly in
when I was working in some health
systems because people had this great
technology. They could move data
quickly. they could do classification
and all this other stuff and they just
wanted to move at Mach 10. I'm like
guys, we don't even let our own people
in my data team produce something that
doesn't get passed by somebody with a
clinical eye. If it's clinical data, it
requires some expertise that's beyond
just being a technician who happens to
be able to read. U you know, I'm not
going to be the guy to step in to answer
clinical questions. No, I've been in
healthcare 30 years, but there's no
literary
MD. There's no such thing that has any
meaning whatsoever. You you can't you
can't have the context. And I think this
is where it bugs me with to what you're
saying about how people using, you know,
the cloud or or whatever you chat GPT is
they won't even know what's relevant in
terms of context.
Exactly.
Things that you would know. I mean, just
being able to look at a patient that's
sitting in front of you that has some
body language is it's telling you
something that they're not saying.
That's exactly right. And and and if you
and this is another thing, you know,
when I started my role at at BMS, I
asked my team, I had 50 people on my
team. I asked them, "How many of you
have actually set foot in a clinical
trial? Have you ever been in and watched
or participated in a clinical trial?"
Because this group's job was to
interpret data from clinical trials. Now
I have come you know my informatics
training is stemmed from having 10 years
of clinical experience on top of you
know the next 30 plus years in in
informatics. So I can look at things
with a lens with a lens that sees both
sides of that coin. And if you don't
have that lens and you just look at the
data without a clinical perspective
you're going to miss stuff. And this is
the democratization problem that I see
that if you don't have and and like when
I found out that only three people out
of 50 actually had ever been involved
with a clinical trial or been watched
like blood drawn for a clinical trial or
been in a place where the patients were
being interviewed by a trial manager
like no one had. I don't know how you do
a job like be a data analyst without
that kind of context. I have no idea. I
set up a program where I sent those
folks out to go get that context. I felt
it was that important and and I think
that other organizations should think
about that as well that clinical
content. So Beth Israel runs a program
for uh at the division of clinical
formatics a fellowship for executives
who are actually already doing their day
jobs who want to learn about the
clinical side of things. It's a it's a I
think it's a threemonth kind of program.
It's not cheap, but it helps get
executives to get that kind of clinical
context and it's something if you're
interested, you can contact Yuri Canana
at the division of clinical informatics
and he has slot. They're not that
they're not that many, but there are
slots and you can get that. It's not a
substitution for your MD. It's not a
substitution for your RN or your vet
degree or your dental degree, but it
gives you at least a taste where most of
these folks never had that before.
Yeah, it's just this is just so
important, you know. We we've got to
make sure that we're we're getting it
right. And I, you know, good intentions
are are are fine, but you be you need
qualified people who are making calls
about political decision-m usefulness of
the research, the validity of it. You
you can't we can't get this wrong. We we
we just can't.
Oh, but we are we we're going to get it
wrong. Let's, you know, don't say we
can't because we will get it wrong. We
will get, you know, the old adage from
medical school is that 50% of the things
they teach you in medical school are
going to be proven to be wrong. Problem
is when you're learning it, you don't
know which 50% is wrong. So it's
inevitable we're going to get it wrong.
We have to have enough tolerance and
enough wisdom to know number one, it's
probably okay to get some of it wrong.
And it's essential to get some So you
only learn when you get something wrong,
right? You don't learn much if you get
everything right. So if you get
something goes sideways when the when
the space shuttle exploded that probably
provided an enormous amount of learnings
for NASA so that you know they would
never launch again during an you know an
icy day so the O-rings wouldn't uh
wouldn't expand and cause problems.
We're talking about something that is so
critical and it's the it's the we're
talking about an evolving science and
we're talking about the practice of
medicine and it's such hugely important
which even trained clinicians with 30
years of experience there's still an
evolving science and there's learnings
there's more more information more
insight coming constantly and sadly
we're also discovering new diseases I
think we're probably doing things that
are causing our problems too but that's
a whole another issue but the the the
important from where I'm sitting is it's
voices like yours who need to be heard.
They need to be out in front and being
the ones that are they're being, you
know, listened to and are making we have
to make sure that organizations are
hearing this and they're reaching out to
somebody like you to understand where
they actually are in their journey and
are they prepared? Do they have the
right pieces in place and have the right
programs for literacy? uh all the things
that you've been talking about. Uh I
think it's just hugely important. Well,
the biggest swing and miss we could have
is if we don't pay attention to your
wishes like yours right now.
Well, not to not to be too blatant in
being self- serving, but if people want
to have a longer conversation or want to
engage Luminant in those kinds of
programs or projects, we are selective
in what we take. We don't take
everything that comes down the pike, but
you could reach out to me. It's the
email is simple. It's steve
luminantconsulting.com and luminant is lu
m i n t luminantconsulting.com
and send me an email and we'd have a
conversation. The sweet spot for us is
looking at the at the overall strategy
and how to implement it. Uh we're not a
data science shop. We're not going to do
projects that revolve around, you know,
analyzing the data. Although we can,
that's not where we find our sweet spot.
Our sweet spot is helping organizations
really put together programs that will
breed sustainability and cut through the
noise and get right down to pure signal.
That's fantastic. And for for the
listeners, uh you you'll find a great
amount of detail in in the show notes
how to get in touch for with Dr. Lov Dr.
Lock, this has been amazing for me. I I
I can't tell you I hope the listeners uh
can appreciate that that the the way
that it was for me. I I learned w you're
you've had a very impressive career and
there there's so much uh great work
ahead of you. You've got the passion to
do it and I can't wait to to to stay in
touch and and find ways that I could be
supportive of what you're doing and and
I I I just know there's a lot of great
stuff coming and I can't thank you
enough uh for for coming on the show.
This has been amazing. Thank you.
Oh, you're quite welcome and I really
appreciate having the time to do this
with you and I I hope that it's helpful
to folks out there. And by the way, if
you do find it helpful, pay it forward.
You know, that's always my motto. Pay it
forward. Help folks who are earlier in
their careers and help them leg up
because, you know, we're not always
going to be here. We need to make sure
the next generation is is getting, you
know, tuned up to do this thoughtfully.
So, pay it forward.
We get along well. I think we're we're
thinking the same way at this point
where we've got this horizon. We want to
make sure we're investing in the next
generation and how they make sure that
they they're they're falling in love
with the the the things that we've been
in love with so that they'll carry it
and we hand it to the generation after
them.
Absolutely. Well, thank you so much for
having me. I really appreciate the
opportunity. That's it for this episode
of the Signal Room. If today's
conversation sparked something in you,
an idea, a challenge, or perspective
worth amplifying, I'd love to hear from
you. Message me on LinkedIn or visit
sigaroompodcast.com
to explore being a guest on an upcoming